Guide to the Harvey Harris Bloom Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harvey Harris Bloom papers
1819-1862
1853-1862
MS 918
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
A journal, short essays and notes, and fourteen letters written by Harvey Harris Bloom to members of his family and friends. The letters describe his life while he was teaching at an academy in Millington, New Jersey and his student years at Yale College (1859-1861) before he enlisted in the Union army. Bloom's journal as well as his writings are largely devoted to religious meditations, but also included are stories, poems, and disputes written while at Yale College.
Bloom, Harvey Harris, 1838-1864
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. W. F. Low, 1958.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Harvey Harris Bloom consist of a journal, short writings, and a few letters. Included are fourteen letters written by Bloom to his brother John and three others to relatives and friends, between 1857 and 1862, while he was teaching at an academy in Millington, New Jersey, and then attending Yale College. The letters contain news of family and friends and describe social events, and contain advice to his brother about school and thoughts on God and nature. One letter to John (1860 Nov 7) concerns Lincoln's election; one to a cousin (1861 Apr 22) describes a massive Union rally in New York City.
The first volume of Bloom's journal covers the period August-December, 1853, while he was at school, and contains meditations on life, education, and friendship, as well as notes on Bloom's activities. The other volume relates in some detail his first journey to Millington in December of 1855 and his return in January of 1857 via Monmouth, New Jersey. Entries for the intervening period consist of brief essays on such subjects as human mortality.
Short writings by Bloom make up the balance of the collection. These include disputations and essays on topics of current politics, education, and so forth, some written while Bloom was at Yale; meditations on faith and religion, including a declaration of his intent to consecrate himself to the service of God; several short gothic stories, poetry, and a few other items. Also in the collection is a deed of Levi and Mary Talmage to Mrs. Jabez Goodell for land in Parma, New York, dating 1819.
Biographical / Historical
Harvey Harris Bloom was born in North Norwich, New York, on August 23, 1838. He entered Yale College with the class of 1862, but left during his junior year in order to fight for the Union Army in the Civil War. Unable to maintain a soldier's life, he returned to Yale and graduated in 1863. Already in poor health, though, Bloom died of consumption on March 18, 1864.
Religion -- 19th century; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Diaries; Educators; Bloom, Harvey Harris, 1838-1864; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1863; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Letters to John C. Bloom, 1858-1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters to others, 1857, 1861, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journal
    - "Thoughts and Sketches, Vol. 1st", 1853 August-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Journal Continued", 1855 December-1856 May, 1857 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings
    - Disputations, 1857, 1862, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Essays, 1858, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Religious writings, 1856-1857 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Short stories, 1853, 1862, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Rules for Life", 1856 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "List of Rolls, Returns, & Reports required of the Co. Commanders", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deed of Levi and Mary Talmage to Mrs. Jabez Goodell, 1819 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 12)